Finding Aid for Bradley v. Milliken case files, 1962-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Bradley v. Milliken case files
  - Trial materials
    - Intervention Documents
      - Motions to intervene
        - Kerry Green et al. and Tri-County Citizens for Intervention
          - Notice of hearing; Motion to intervene; Answers, counterclaim and cross-complaint of defendants-intervenor; Memorandum in support of motion to intervene December 1971 (Box 3)
            (3-13)
          - Amended motion to intervene and accompanying documents March 1972 (Box 3)
            (3-14)
          - Motions to vacate intervention restrictions, for a class defense order, for a conditional dismissal of complaint for failure to comply with mandatory requirement of FRCP rule 19(c) and to vacate November 5, 1972 order in part, January 1973 (Box 3)
            (3-15)
        - Southfield Public Schools February 1972 (Box 3)
          (3-16)
        - School District of the City of Royal Oak February 1972 (Box 3)
          (3-17)
        - Grosse Pointe Public School System February 1972 (Box 3)
          (3-18)
        - Allen Park Public Schools et al. February 1972 (Box 3)
          (3-19)
        - City of Warren March 1972 (Box 3)
          (3-20)
        - United States of America Justice Department March-May 1972 (Box 3)
          (3-21)
        - Professional Personnel of Van Dyke et al. July 1973 (Box 3)
          (3-22)
    - Transportation Documents
      - Motion to require purchase of transportation equipment; Memoranda in support of and opposition to motion April 1972 (Box 3)
        (3-23)
      - Motion to modify the order enjoining construction pendente lite; Memorandum in support of motion, April 1972 (Box 3)
        (3-24)
      - Order requiring defendants State Board of Education and State Superintendent of Public Instruction to make a survey and evaluation of existing school transportation facilities April 1972 (Box 3)
        (3-25)
      - Survey and evaluation of existing school transportation facilities by defendants State Board of Education and State Superintendent of Public Instruction (First Report) April 1972 (Box 3)
        (3-26)
      - Survey and evaluation of existing school transportation facilities by defendants State Board of Education and State Superintendent of Public Instruction (Final Report) May 1972 (Box 3)
        (3-27)
      - Affidavit of Southfield Public Schools re: transportation May 1972 (Box 3)
        (3-28)
      - [State Superintendent of Public Instruction's] Progress in preparing recommendations for appropriate interim and final arrangements for the (1) financial, (2) administrative and school governance, and (3) contractual arrangements for the operation of the schools within the desegregation area June 1972 (Box 3)
        (3-29)
      - Recommendations of Desegregation Panel regarding additional transportation equipment needed for the implementation of an interim desegregation plan July 1972 (Box 3)
        (3-30)
    - Pleadings
      - Docket 1970-1973 (Box 3)
        (incomplete record of documents)
        (3-31)
      - Attorney rosters 1971-1972 (Box 3)
        (3-32)
      - Pre trial statements, preliminary order and assorted materials 1970-1971 (Box 3)
        (3-33)
      - Briefs, memoranda, orders, etc. (incomplete collection; generally arranged by docket number but date ranges include outlying materials)
        - 1971 (Box 3)
          (3-34)
        - 1972
          - February 14-May 5, 1972 (Box 3)
            (3-35)
          - May 5-May 9, 1972 (Box 3)
            (3-36)
          - May 10-June 29, 1972 (Box 3)
            (3-37)
          - June 28-August 13, 1972 (Box 3)
            (3-38)
          - August 15-September 7, 1972 (Box 4)
            (4-1)
          - September 11-December 8, 1972 (Box 4)
            (4-2)
        - 1973
          - February 8-October 15, 1973 (Box 4)
            (4-3)
          - October 16-October 19, 1973 (Box 4)
            (4-4)
          - October 23-December 27, 1973 (Box 4)
            (4-5)
        - 1974 (Box 4)
          (4-6)
    - Exhibit materials of plaintiffs and defendants 1970-1972 (Box 4)
      (unarranged)
      (4-7)
    - Transcripts
      - Initial injunction proceedings
        - Motion to intervene in the above-entitled cause before Honorable Stephen J. Roth August 27, 1970 (Box 4)
          (4-8)
        - Proceedings had on Plan A and Plan B, in the above-entitled cause before Honorable Stephen J. Roth November 18, 1970 (Box 4)
          (4-9)
        - Continuation of proceedings had on Plan A and Plan B, in the above-entitled cause before Honorable Stephen J. Roth November 19, 1970 (Box 4)
          (4-10)
        - Conclusion of proceedings had on Plan A and Plan B, in the above-entitled cause before Honorable Stephen J. Roth November 25, 1970 (Box 4)
          (4-11)
      - Proceedings on violations (de jure segregation)
        - February 11, 1971 (Box 5)
          ("Proceedings had on standing of plaintiffs and under Rule 23, Federal Rules of Civil Procedure")
          (5-1)
        - March 22, 1971 (Box 5)
          (5-2)
        - April 5,1971 (Box 5)
          (5-3)
        - April 6, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 1)
          (5-4)
        - April 7, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 2)
          (5-5)
        - April 8, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 3)
          (5-6)
        - April 13, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 4)
          (5-7)
        - April 14, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 5)
          (5-8)
        - April 15, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 6)
          (5-9)
        - April 16, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 7)
          (5-10)
        - April 27, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 8)
          (5-11)
        - April 28, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 9)
          (5-12)
        - April 29, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 10)
          (5-13)
        - April 30, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 11)
          (5-14)
        - May 4, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 12)
          (5-15)
        - May 5, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 13)
          (5-16)
        - May 6, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 14)
          (5-17)
        - May 7, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 15)
          (5-18)
        - May 11, 1971 (Box 5)
          (Book 16)
          (5-19)
        - May 12, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 17)
          (6-1)
        - May 13, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 18)
          (6-2)
        - May 14, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 19)
          (6-3)
        - May 18, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 20)
          (6-4)
        - May 19, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 21)
          (6-5)
        - May 20, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 22)
          (6-6)
        - May 21, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 23)
          (6-7)
        - June 2, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 24)
          (6-8)
        - June 3, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 25)
          (6-9)
        - June 4, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 26)
          (6-10)
        - June 8, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 27)
          (6-11)
        - June 9, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 28)
          (6-12)
        - June 10, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 29)
          (6-13)
        - June 15, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 30)
          (6-14)
        - June 16, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 31)
          (6-15)
        - June 17, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 32)
          (6-16)
        - June 18, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 33)
          (6-17)
        - June 22, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 34)
          (6-18)
        - June 23, 1971 (Box 6)
          (Book 35)
          (6-19)
        - June 24, 1971 (Box 7)
          (Book 36)
          (7-1)
        - June 25, 1971 (Box 7)
          (Book 37)
          (7-2)
        - July 15, 1971 (Box 7)
          (Book 38)
          (7-3)
        - July 19, 1971 (Box 7)
          (Book 39)
          (7-4)
        - July 20, 1971 (Box 7)
          (Book 40)
          (7-5)
        - July 22, 1971 (Box 7)
          (Book 41)
          (7-6)
        - July 26, 1971 (Box 7)
          (Book 42)
          (7-7)
      - Remedy proceedings
        - Detroit only plans
          - October 4, 1971 (Box 7)
            (7-8)
          - December 20, 1971 (Box 7)
            (7-9)
          - February 22, 1972 (Box 7)
            (Motions to intervene, et al., in the above-entitled matter)
            (7-10)
          - March 14, 1972 (Box 7)
            (Book I)
            (7-11)
          - March 15, 1972 (Box 7)
            (Book II)
            (7-12)
          - March 16, 1972 (Box 7)
            (Book III)
            (7-13)
          - March 17, 1972 (Box 7)
            (Book IV)
            (7-14)
          - March 21, 1972 (Box 7)
            (Book V)
            (7-15)
        - Metropolitan plans
          - March 28, 1972 (Box 7)
            (7-16)
          - March 29, 1972 (Box 7)
            (7-17)
          - March 30, 1972 (Box 7)
            (7-18)
          - April 4, 1972 (Box 7)
            (7-19)
          - April 5, 1972 (Box 7)
            (7-20)
          - April 6, 1972 (Box 8)
            (Book VI)
            (8-1)
          - April 7, 1972 (Box 8)
            (Book VII)
            (8-2)
          - April 11, 1972 (Box 8)
            (Book VIII)
            (8-3)
          - April 12, 1972 (Box 8)
            (Book IX)
            (8-4)
          - (Book X April 13, 1972 is missing) (Box 8)
          - April 14, 1972 (Box 8)
            (Book XI)
            (8-5)
      - Depositions
        - Continuation of deposition of Merle Henrickson, taken by plaintiffs April 12, 1971 (Box 8)
          (8-6)
        - De bene esse deposition of Dr. Norman Drachler taken by Defendant Detroit Board of Education June 28, 1971 (Box 8)
          (8-7)
        - The deposition of Harold Wagner, taken on behalf of the plaintiffs March 22, 1972 (Box 8)
          (8-8)
        - Exhibits from the deposition of Harold Wagner March 22, 1972 (Box 8)
          (8-9)
        - The deposition of John Porter, Ph.D., taken on behalf of plaintiffs March 23, 1972 (Box 8)
          (8-10)
      - Miscellaneous motions and transcripts
        - Rulings on motions taken under advisement during trial before Honorable Stephen J. Roth June 14, 1972 (Box 8)
          (8-11)
        - Motion to expand panel, temporary injunction, stay of proceedings, et al., in the above-entitled cause before Honorable Stephen J. Roth June 29, 1972 (Box 8)
          (8-12)
        - Proceedings had in the above-entitled matter re: purchase of buses before Honorable Stephen J. Roth July 10, 1972 (Box 8)
          (8-13)
        - Motion for stay: proceedings had in the above-entitled matter before Honorable Stephen J. Roth July 13, 1972 (Box 8)
          (8-14)
        - Proceedings had before Honorable Stephen J. Roth July 19, 1972 (Box 8)
          (8-15)
  - Appellate Materials
    The Appellate Materials subseries documents hearings and orders in the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit as well as in the United States Supreme Court. Content includes petitions for writ of certiorari with supporting appendices; briefs filed by defendants, intervening defendants, and plaintiffs; and related amicus curiae briefs.
    - Bloomfield Hills School District v. Stephen J. Roth, Docket No. 72-1651 in the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit
      - Petition for writ of mandamus and/or prohibition June, 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-16)
      - Correspondence with Richard Scrughm, Deputy Clerk June 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-17)
      - Letter supplementing the petition filed by Bloomfield Hills School District July 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-18)
      - Petition for rehearing and suggestion for hearing in banc July 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-19)
      - Order denying petition for rehearing August 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-20)
    - West Bloomfield School District, et al., v. the Honorable Stephen J. Roth, Docket No. 72-1670 in the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit
      - Petition for writ of prohibition and mandamus July 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-21)
      - Correspondence and transcripts related to petition for writ of prohibition and mandamus July 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-22)
      - Petition for rehearing of petition for writ of prohibition and mandamus and suggestion of in banc hearing; Brief in support of petition for rehearing July 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-23)
      - Order denying petition for rehearing August 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-24)
    - School District of the city of Birmingham v. the Honorable Stephen J. Roth, Docket No. 72-1771 in the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit
      - Petition for rehearing of petition for writ of prohibition and/or mandamus August 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-25)
      - Order denying petition for rehearing September 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-26)
    - Michigan Education Association v. Stephen J. Roth, Docket No. 72-8002 in the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit
      - Petition for writ of prohibition and/or mandamus or to intervene in action no. 72-8002 August 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-27)
      - Brief in support of petition for writ of prohibition and/or mandamus or to intervene in action no. 72-8002 August 1972 (Box 8)
        (8-28)
    - Plaintiffs' correspondence to defendants' counsel and the Honorable Stephen J. Roth 1972 (Box 8)
      (8-29)
    - Brief of intervenor school districts in the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit, 1972 (Box 8)
      (8-30)
    - In the Supreme Court of the United States (Docket No. 73-434, which consolidates 73-435 and 73-436) (Box 9)
      - Petition for writ of certiorari to the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit May 1972 (Box 9)
        (Milliken et al., petitioners, v. Bradley et al.)
        (9-1)
      - Petitions for writ of certiorari to the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit 1972 (Box 9)
        (various petitioners)
        (9-2)
      - Petitions for writ of certiorari to the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit 1973 (Box 9)
        (9-3)
      - Various briefs, reply briefs, memoranda, and appendices on writ of certiorari to the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit 1973 (Box 9)
        (9-4)
      - Appendix to petition for writ of certiorari (overview of Bradley v. Milliken in U.S. District Court and U.S. Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit), 1973 (Box 9)
        (9-5)
      - Joint appendix to petition for writ of certiorari
        - Volume I: Pleadings 1973 (Box 9)
          (9-6)
        - Volume II: Transcript, segregation hearings 1973 (Box 9)
          (9-7)
        - Volume III: Transcript, segregation hearings 1973 (Box 9)
          (9-8)
        - Volume IV: Transcript, intra-city plans and metropolitan hearings 1973 (Box 9)
          (9-9)
        - Volume V: Exhibits and depositions 1973 (Box 9)
          (9-10)
      - Motions for leave to file brief amicus curiae and briefs amicus curiae in support of petitioners 1973 (Box 9)
        (various school districts)
        (9-11)
      - Brief amicus curiae of city of Hartford, Connecticut in support of respondent, Bradley 1973 (Box 9)
        (9-12)
  - Opinions and Orders
    The Opinions and Orders subseries covers major opinions Judge Roth issued in the course of handling Bradley v. Milliken. In addition to true copies of prominent decisions, the subseries includes Roth's drafts and related materials from the development of the September 27, 1971 "Ruling on Issue of Segregation" and the June 14, 1972 "Ruling on Desegregation Area and Order for Development of Plan of Desegregation" and related "Findings of Fact and Conclusions of Law." Also present are various Sixth Circuit orders and the full text of the Supreme Court's majority and minority opinions from its 1974 decision.
    - United States District Court, Eastern District of Michigan, Southern Division
      - Drafts, notes and related materials for various findings and rulings issued by the Honorable Stephen J. Roth
        - Ruling, findings of fact, and conclusions of law on school segregation September 1971 (Box 9)
          (9-13)
        - Ruling and order on petitions for intervention March 1972 (Box 9)
          (9-14)
        - Findings of fact and conclusions of law on Detroit intra-city plans for desegregation March 1972 (Box 9)
          (9-15)
        - Ruling on propriety of considering a metropolitan remedy to accomplish desegregation of the public schools of the city of Detroit March 1972 (Box 9)
          (9-16)
        - Ruling, findings of fact and conclusions of law on desegregation area and order for development of plan of desegregation June 1972 (Box 9)
          (9-17)
        - Various rulings and orders 1970-1973 (Box 9)
          (9-18)
      - Order to show cause why a preliminary injunction should not issue August 19, 1970 (Box 10)
        (10-1)
      - Rulings on: Application for preliminary injunction; Motion to intervene; motion to dismiss as to defendants Milliken and Kelley September 3, 1970 (Box 10)
        (10-2)
      - Ruling of the Court on motion to implement April 7, 1970 plan, November 4, 1970 (Box 10)
        (10-3)
      - Preliminary pre trial order and memoranda November 4, 1970 (Box 10)
        (10-4)
      - Ruling on school plans submitted December 3, 1970 (Box 10)
        (10-5)
      - Ruling on motion for continuance December 3, 1970 (Box 10)
        (10-6)
      - Order on continuance February 2, 1971 (Box 10)
        (10-7)
      - Ruling on motion; Ruling on standing of plaintiffs February 16, 1971 (Box 10)
        (10-8)
      - Class action order February 16, 1971 (Box 10)
        (10-9)
      - Supplemental pre-trial order February 16, 1971 (Box 10)
        (10-10)
      - Ruling on issue of segregation September 27, 1971 (Box 10)
        (10-11)
      - Ruling and order on petitions for intervention March 15, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-12)
      - Ruling on propriety of considering a metropolitan remedy to accomplish desegregation of the public schools of the city of Detroit March 24, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-13)
      - Findings of fact and conclusions of law on Detroit-only plans of desegregation March 28, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-14)
      - Ruling on desegregation area and order for development of plan of desegregation June 14, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-15)
      - Findings of fact and conclusions of law in support of ruling on desegregation area and development of plan June 14, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-16)
      - Rulings and order on motions and other matters heard June 14, 1972, June 29, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-17)
      - Order modifying order for development of plan of desegregation, to add additional panel members June 30, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-18)
      - Preliminary injunction June 30, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-19)
      - Record entry of notice of hearing and procedure for future notices; Order denying motion for stay of proceedings July 7, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-20)
      - Order for acquisition of transportation July 11, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-21)
      - Order denying motion for stay of order for acquisition for transportation July 11, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-22)
      - Order relating to the certification under the provisions of 28 U.S.C. 1292(b) in connection with certain orders and rulings of the court heretofore entered July 20, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-23)
      - Order on defendants' motion for extension of time August 15, 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-24)
      - Order shortening time to answer or respond to motion and setting time for hearing of motion November 28, 1972 (Box 10)
        (issued by the Honorable Fred W. Kaess)
        (10-25)
      - Order granting intervention to the Professional Personnel of Van Dyke July 16, 1973 (Box 10)
        (10-26)
      - Order to join school districts and their superintendents as defendants September 10, 1973 (Box 10)
        (10-27)
      - Order to amend nunc pro tunc October 19, 1973 (Box 10)
        (10-28)
    - United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit
      - No. 21036 decision February 1971 (Box 10)
        (10-29)
      - Nos. 72-106472-1066 order February 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-30)
      - No. 72-1811 order November 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-31)
      - Nos. 72-1809 -- 72-1814
        - Decision December 1972 (Box 10)
          (10-32)
        - Order for rehearing in banc January 1973 (Box 10)
          (10-33)
        - Decision June 1973 (Box 10)
          (10-34)
      - No. 72-1831 order August 1972 (Box 10)
        (10-35)
      - No. 72-8002
        - Response by defendant-intervenor-appellants Kerry Green, et al., to request of counsel for concurrence in emergency application for stay circa July 1972 (Box 10)
          (10-36)
        - Order July 1972 (Box 10)
          (10-37)
        - Motion for clarification and/or modification of stay order September 1972 (Box 10)
          (10-38)
      - No. 72-2008 order July 1973 (Box 10)
        (10-39)
    - Supreme Court of the United States: opinions and assorted documents 1974 (Box 10)
      (10-40)
  - Law Notes of Stephen J. Roth
    The Law Notes of Stephen J. Roth subseries illustrates the process by which Roth made various decisions and handled the case. It consists of annotated briefs, typed and handwritten notes, correspondence related to the case, and materials related to legal precedents and concurrent desegregation trials. The notes themselves relate to procedural details in the management of his courtroom in addition to legal notes related to his opinions and orders.
    - 1970-1973 (Box 10)
      (10-41; 10-42; contents of 10-41 were originally housed in a binder)
  - Published materials
    The Published Materials subseries has two main components: several volumes of the Federal Supplement in which Bradley v. Milliken is reviewed and a large collection of newspaper clippings. These latter materials, gathered from Detroit-area and national newspapers, provide a particularly rich context for the case files by illustrating public opinions and reactions to the case. In addition to covering the process of desegregation and the case itself, the clippings detail activist Irene McCabe's battle against busing, school boycotts, acts of violence related to desegregation, and the role the case played in the 1972 presidential election in Michigan and elsewhere.
    - Federal Supplements
      - Vol. 338, no. 2 (Box 10)
        (10-43)
      - Vol. 345, no. 2 (Box 10)
        (10-44)
    - Clippings (Box 11)
      - Undated, 2 folders (Box 11)
        (11-1; 11-2)
      - 1962 (Box 11)
        (11-3)
      - 1970, 2 folders (Box 11)
        (11-4; 11-5)
      - 1971, 2 folders (Box 11)
        (11-6; 11-7)
      - 1972, 4 folders (Box 11)
        (11-8, etc.-11-11)
      - 1973, 3 folders (Box 11)
        (11-12, etc.-11-14)
      - 1974, 2 folders (Box 11)
        (11-15; 11-16)
      - 1975 (Box 11)
        (11-17)
      - 1976 (Box 11)
        (11-18)
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence subseries is divided into two main sections, "Professional" and "Citizens." The former contains letters to and from attorneys of record, other judges working on desegregation cases, participants in the trial, and various legal professionals. The latter consists of letters to and from individuals, groups, and municipalities expressing support or opposition to developments in Bradley v. Milliken.
    - Professional: letters to and from attorneys, judges, and participants involved with Milliken v. Bradley or similar cases
      - 1970 (Box 11)
        (11-19)
      - 1971, 2 folders (Box 11)
        (11-20; 11-21)
      - 1972, 3 folders (Box 11)
        (11-22. etc.-11-24)
      - 1973 (Box 11)
        (11-25)
      - 1974 (Box 11)
        (11-26)
    - Citizens: letters to and from individuals, groups, and municipalities expressing support or opposition to developments in Milliken v. Bradley